Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the League for Industrial Democracy PE.033
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the League for Industrial Democracy
1905-1986
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Tamiment Library
PE.033
2 Linear Feet (2 boxes)
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the League for Industrial Democracy is an artificial collection, collected and assembled by the Tamiment Library over the course of several decades. Founded in 1905, the LID is an educational organization focusing on increasing democracy in cultural, political and economic life. The collection consists of printed ephemera put out by the group nationally, including, fliers, brochures, leaflets, publications lists, pamphlets and songbooks. Also included in the collection are materials from affiliated and precursor groups, the Intercollegiate League for Industrial Democracy, the Intercollegiate Socialist Society, and the Student League for Industrial Democracy. There are also a few files from local LID chapters from Akron, Ohio, Boston, Massachusetts and New York City.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Scope and Content Note
The Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Printed Ephemera Collection on the League for Industrial Democracy consists of a selection of printed matter, including: fliers, pamphlets, brochures, songbooks, bulletins as well as constitutions, membership cards and applications.
Series I: General Files, 1923-1986, consists of printed ephemera from the League of Industrial Democracy, largely published at the national level. There are a number of pamphlets in this series, arranged by date and at times by author or subject. Prominent authors include, Harry Laidler, Norman Thomas and Michael Harrington. Also included in this series are the publicity materials related to the LIDs annual luncheons, which were in effect anniversary celebrations and give introductory information about the League. There is a short history provided in this series as well. Also included are files from local chapters in Akron, Ohio, Boston, Massachusetts and New York City.
Series II: Affiliated and Youth Organizations, 1905-1959, consists of material from the Intercollegiate Socialist Society (ISS), the Intercollegiate League for Industrial Democracy, and the Student League for Industrial Democracy. The ISS was a precursor to the LID, formed in 1905. From this organization, the collection contains pamphlets, fliers, brochures for conferences, and guides to courses in studying socialism. From the Student League for Industrial Democracy, the youth wing of the LID, the collection consists of pamphlets, songbooks, fliers and brochures, as well as publications including a brief history and an organizer's manual.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Harry Laidler Papers (TAM 047)
Intercollegiate Socialist Society Records (TAM 048)
Michael Harrington Papers (TAM 209)
Andre Schiffrin: Student League for Industrial Democracy Files (TAM 419)
Harry Wellington Laidler Photographs (PHOTOS 009)
Historical/Biographical Note
The League for Industrial Democracy, also known as the LID, was founded in 1905 by such notables as Norman Thomas, Jack London and Clarence Darrow. The group, originally named the Intercollegiate Socialist Society, focused its attention primarily on educating college students about socialism and the labor movement. In 1921, the organization took on its current name. Still addressing students, the LID was home to what became the Students for a Democratic Society, then known as the Student League for Industrial Democracy. Taking a stance on communism became a divisive issue between the two groups. The organizations diverged following the Students for a Democratic Society's convention in Port Huron, Michigan in 1960. The LID continued to produce lecture and discussion guides as well as host conferences and study commissions to achieve their goal of increasing democracy in the economic, political, and cultural life. The organization also published numerous pamphlets on socialism, labor issues, totalitarianism and democracy.
Custodial History
The provenance of the materials is varied. Items were obtained through purchases, donations, standing orders with publishers, arrangements with labor unions and other organizations, exchanges with other libraries, and through ongoing collecting by Tamiment staff.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into two series: Series I: General Files, 1923-1986; Series II: Affiliated and Youth Organizations, 1905-1959. Folders are arranged alphabetically within series.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials in this collection have been compiled by the Tamiment Library.
Materials found in the repository were added to the collection in 2014. The accession number associated with this material is 2014.091.
Constitutions.; Student movements -- United States.; Socialism and youth -- United States.; Printed ephemera.; Student movements.; Songbooks.; Pamphlets.; Fliers (printed matter); Brochures.; Bulletins.; Student movements |z New York (State) |z New York.; Intercollegiate Socialist Society (U.S.); League for Industrial Democracy; Student League for Industrial Democracy (U.S.); Thomas, Norman, 1884-1968
- Series I: General Files, 1923-1986
  - Akron Chapter (OH), 1952 (Box 1)
  - Annual Luncheon (Anniversaries), 1935-1954 (Box 1)
  - Annual Luncheon (Anniversaries), 1955-1959 (Box 1)
  - Annual Luncheon (Anniversaries), 1961-1986 (Box 1)
  - Annual Conference, 1946-1980 (Box 1)
  - Annual and Financial Reports, 1962-1980 (Box 1)
  - Birthday Celebrations (John Dewey and Harry Laidler), 1949-1950, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Board of Directors, 1925-1973 (Box 1)
  - Boston Branch, 1939-1940 (Box 1)
  - Brochures, 1923-1969, undated (Box 1)
  - Circular Letters and Memoranda, 1923-1986, undated (Box 1)
  - Conferences, 1927-1943 (Box 1)
  - Constitutions, 1972-1973, undated (Box 1)
  - Event Invitations and Fliers (Michael Harrington installed as Chairman of the Board, and others), 1925-1964, undated (Box 1)
  - Executive Committee: Minutes, 1962-1973 (Box 1)
  - History of, undated (Box 1)
  - Labor Issues Paper Series, undated (Box 1)
  - Lectures, Symposium, Institutes: Fliers and Brochures, 1932-1974, undated (Box 1)
  - Membership (Cards, Applications for, and Invitations), 1941-1976, undated (Box 1)
  - New York Chapter, 1927-1968 (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets, 1920-1929 (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets I, 1930-1939 (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets II, 1930-1939 (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets I, 1940-1949 (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets II, 1940-1949 (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets, 1950-1959 (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets, 1960-1969 (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets, 1970-1979 (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets, 1980-, undated (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets: Fascism, 1934, undated (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets: Great Britain, 1943-1951 (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets: Harrington, Michael, 1965-1967 (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets: Laidler, Harry, 1924-1952 (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets: Looking Forward Series, 1932-1937 (Box 1)
  - Pamphlets: Looking Forward Series, 1965-1971 (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets: Thomas, Norman, 1925-1953, undated (Box 2)
  - Pamphlets: "What is the L.I.D.?", undated (Box 2)
  - Press Releases, 1942-1964 (Box 2)
  - Publication and Book Lists/Fliers, 1923-1971, undated (Box 2)
  - Publications About, 1935 (Box 2)
  - Publications/Articles by, 1957-1983, undated (Box 2)
  - Reports and Position Papers, 1930-1970 (Box 2)
- Series II: Affiliated and Youth Organizations, 1905-1959
  - Intercollegiate League for Industrial Democracy, 1921-1933 (Box 2)
  - Intercollegiate Socialist Society, 1905-1919 (Box 2)
  - Student League for Industrial Democracy, 1935-1959 (Box 2)
  - Student League for Industrial Democracy: Fliers and Brochures, undated (Box 2)
  - Student League for Industrial Democracy: History of, 1953 (Box 2)
  - Student League for Industrial Democracy: National Convention, 1948, 1957 (Box 2)
  - Student League for Industrial Democracy: Pamphlets and Publications, 1934-1946 (Box 2)
  - Student League for Industrial Democracy: Pamphlets and Publications, undated (Box 2)
  - Student League for Industrial Democracy: Songbooks, undated (Box 2)
  - Student League for Industrial Democracy: Summer Institute/School, 1935-1957 (Box 2)
  - Students for a Democratic Society, Relationship with and Student Activities Committee, 1962-1970 (Box 2)